American Foundation for Continuing Education (AFCE) Records
American Foundation for Continuing Education (AFCE) Records
1947-1965
American Foundation for Continuing Education
19 linear ft
Administrative files, general correspondence, financial documents, programs and projects (conferences, workshops, seminars), and publications. Individual correspondents include William W. Cowan, Stanley A. Gill, Charles A. Nelson, George W. Overton, William J. Trainor, Harold S. Williams, and Jerome M. Ziegler as well as officials from the Fund for Adult Education (FAE).
148809
Biographical History
Beginning in 1947 as the American Foundation for Political Education, this organization developed liberal education materials for study-discussion programs focused on politics, law, and international affairs; helped organizations, agencies, and institutions through consultation, program development, and leadership training; and prepared special materials on liberal arts and politics for business and industry. In the late 1950’s the Foundation’s subject interests, publications, and clientele grew and encompassed the fields of economics, science, the arts, and the humanities, thus prompting the Foundation to change its name to the American Foundation for Continuing Education. The Foundation garnered financial support largely by grants from the Fund for Adult Education, as well as participants’s fees and service charges. The Foundation ended most of its activities other than publications and revisions in 1965.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Administrative files contain annual reports, board of directors minutes, meeting reports and agendas, funding information, staff meetings, and miscellany. Correspondence has four divisions: general correspondence (1953-1970); individuals and organizations; outgoing (1962-1969); subject. Key Foundation names appear as correspondents; William W. Cowan, Stanley A. Gill, Charles A. Nelson, George W. Overton, William J. Trainor, Harold S. Williams, and Jerome M. Ziegler; as well as officials from the Fund for Adult Education. Financial documents include account books, auditor and bank statements, income tax and related papers, payroll records, and other common financial data. Programs and projects include conferences, workshops, and seminars sponsored by the Foundation or in which the Foundation played a role. Of note, Arms and Foreign Policy Program (1962), Avenue to the Arts (1959-1963), Explorations of the Universe (1961-1963), Peace Corps Project (1960’s), and Science Program (1959-1964). Publications include discussion manuals and papers. Subject files have material of organizations with which the Foundation had contact. Miscellaneous papers consist of newsletters and an assortment of printed material.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Cowan, William Wallace; Gill, Stanley A.; Nelson, Charles A.; Overton, George W.; Trainor, William J.; Williams, Harold S.; Ziegler, Jerome M.; American Foundation for Continuing Education.; American Foundation for Political Education.; Fund for Adult Education (U.S.); Peace Corps (U.S.); Adult education.; Art -- Study and teaching.; International relations.; Science -- Study and teaching.; Correspondence.; Manuals (instructional materials); Minutes (administrative records); Reports.; Teachers.; Adult education
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Administrative files
  - "AFCE - Origin and Philosophical Basis", undated (Box 1)
  - Administrative manual, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Advisors
    - Advisors to AFCE, 1961-1965 (Box 1)
    - Foundation advisors, 1960 (Box 1)
    - New, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
    - Renewed, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Annual reports, 1952; 1968 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors minutes
    - 1947 Apr 17 - 1952 Jun 30 (Box 1)
    - 1952 Aug 6 - 1953 Apr 1 (Box 2)
    - 1953 May 9 - 1954 Apr 1 (Box 2)
    - 1954 May - 1955 May (Box 3)
    - 1955 Jun - 1956 Jun (Box 3)
    - 1956 Jul - 1957 Jun (Box 3)
    - 1957 Jul 1 - 1958 Jun 30 (Box 4)
    - 1958 Jul 1 - 1959 Jun 30 (Box 4)
    - 1959 Jul 1 - 1960 Jun 30 (Box 4)
    - 1960 Jul 1 - 1961 Jun 30 (Box 5)
    - 1961 Jul - 1961 Dec (Box 5)
  - Board of directors minutes, meeting reports and agendas
    - 1962 Jun 2 (Box 5)
    - 1962 Nov 3 (Box 5)
    - 1963 Jun 8 (Box 5)
    - 1963 Dec 7 (Box 5)
    - 1964 May 15 (Box 6)
    - 1964 May 23 (Box 6)
    - 1964 Nov 14 (Box 6)
    - 1967 Feb 2 (Box 6)
  - By-laws, 1953 (Box 6)
  - Corporate minutes and by-laws, draft forms, 1959 (Box 6)
  - Funding
    - Foundation proposals, grants, 1963 (Box 6)
    - Fund for Adult Education, grants, 1960-1967 (Box 6)
    - Johnson Foundation, grants, 1961 (Box 6)
    - Stern Family Fund, 1966 (Box 6)
  - Inter-office memoranda, 1959; 1960-1962 (Box 6)
  - Memoranda, various, 1955-1962 (Box 6)
  - Personnel
    - File, 1960-1962 (Box 6)
    - Resumes, various dates (Box 6)
    - Science administration and programs, 1960-1963 (Box 6)
  - Staff meetings
    - 1955-1957, notes (Box 7)
    - 1961 Nov (Box 7)
    - 1962 Jan (Box 7)
    - 1962 May (Box 7)
    - 1962 Jul (Box 7)
  - Staff memoranda, 1962-1963 (Box 7)
  - Statistical information (AFPE), 1955 (Box 7)
    See also Subject files: American Foundation for Political Education
  - Termination of AFCE, 1965 (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous
    - AFCE transfer to Aspen, CO, 1965 (Box 7)
    - Future of AFCE (Trainor memorandum), 1963 (Box 7)
    - New York Office, transfer of, 1963 (Box 7)
    - New York State registration papers, 1953 (Box 7)
- Correspondence
  - General files
    - 1953-1960 (Box 7)
    - 1961 Jan 1 - Aug 31 (Box 7)
    - 1961 Sep 1 - Oct 31 (Box 7)
    - 1961 Nov 1 - Dec 31 (Box 8)
    - 1962 Jan 1 - Mar 31 (Box 8)
    - 1962 Apr 1 - Jun 30 (Box 8)
    - 1962 Jul 1 - Dec 31 (Box 8)
    - 1963 (Box 8)
    - 1964 (Box 8)
    - 1965 (Box 9)
    - 1966 Jan 1 - Jun 30 (Box 9)
    - 1966 Jul 1 - Dec 31 (Box 9)
    - 1967-1970 (Box 9)
  - Individual files
    - Arden House Conference, 1959 (Box 9)
    - Bell and Howell, 1960-1961 (Box 9)
    - Boardman, Harry, 1959-1964 (Box 9)
    - Brooks, Shepherd, 1957-1961 (Box 9)
    - Chagy, Gideon, 1959-1962 (Box 9)
    - Crohn, Richard J., 1956-1961 (Box 10)
    - Daedalus, 1960-1962 (Box 10)
    - Development and planning committee, 1961 (Box 10)
    - Financial committee, 1957-1962 (Box 10)
    - Geldzahler, Walter S., 1961 (Box 10)
    - General Electric Co., 1959-1960 (Box 10)
    - General Foods Corp., 1959-1960 (Box 10)
    - Harlan, H.C., 1960-1965 (Box 10)
    - Johnson, Robert B., 1961-1962 (Box 10)
    - Kendall College, 1966-1967 (Box 10)
    - Moldof, Edwin, 1961 (Box 10)
    - Nelson, Charles A., 1960-1964 (Box 10)
    - Oceana Publications Ltd., 1962-1964 (Box 10)
    - Percy, Charles H., 1960 (Box 10)
    - Pickus, Robert, 1959-1961 (Box 10)
    - President's Commission on National Goals, 1960 (Box 10)
    - Raymond, Bernard, 1960-1962 (Box 10)
    - Stone, Sumner, 1958-1961 (Box 10)
    - Trainor, William J., 1952-1962 (Box 10)
    - University of Chicago staff, 1960-1962 (Box 10)
    - Washington office, 1961 (Box 10)
  - Outgoing files
    - 1962 Jan-Feb (Box 11)
    - 1962 Mar (Box 11)
    - 1962 Apr-May (Box 11)
    - 1962 Jun-Dec (Box 11)
    - 1963 Jan-Apr (Box 11)
    - 1963 May-Aug (Box 11)
    - 1963 Sep-Dec (Box 11)
    - 1964 Jan-Jun (Box 11)
    - 1964 Jul-Dec (Box 12)
    - 1965 Jan-Jun (Box 12)
    - 1967 Mar-Jun (Box 12)
    - 1967 Jul-Dec (Box 12)
    - 1968 Feb-Dec (Box 12)
    - 1969 Jan-Jun (Box 12)
- Financial documents
  - Account books
    - 1957-1958 (Box 15)
    - 1958-1959, 6 folders (Box 15, 16)
    - 1960-1962, 5 folders (Box 16)
    - 1962-1963, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Auditors' statements, 1952-1958; 4 folders (Box 17)
  - Bank books, 1960-1969 (Box 18)
  - Bank records, 1963-1965 (Box 18)
  - Bank statements
    - General account, 1959-1963 (Box 18)
    - Operating fund account, 1959-1963 (Box 18)
    - Payroll account, 1959-1963 (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous, 1959-1963; 1965-1969 (Box 18)
  - Budget, 1954-1955; 1962-1963 (Box 18)
  - Check books, 1959-1960; 3 folders (Box 19)
  - Financial statements, 1960; 1964-1968; 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Income tax and related papers
    - 1948-1956, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - 1957-1962, 1965, 1967-1968, 5 folders (Box 20)
  - Lease papers, 1953-1958
  - Payroll records
    - 1951, 1953-1956, 1958, 6 folders (Box 20)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 21)
  - Sales tax exemptions (municipal), 1957 (Box 21)
  - Working papers, 3 folders (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous
    - American Foundation for Political Education, 1948 (Box 21)
    - Salary scales, 1954-1956 (Box 21)
- Programs and projects
  - African Leadership Project
    See also Subject Files: African Leadership Project
    - Funding, 1961-1963 (Box 22)
    - Memoranda and various papers, 1961-1963 (Box 22)
    - Proposal, 1962 (Box 22)
  - Area Redevelopment Administration, 1962-1963 (Box 22)
  - Arms and Foreign Policy Program
    - Memoranda, 1962 (Box 22)
    - Sessions I-II, International Politics, 1962 (Box 22)
    - Session III, 1962 (Box 22)
    - Session IV, Force and Foreign Policy, 1962 (Box 22)
    - Session V, The Cold War, 1962 (Box 22)
    - Session VI, Thermonuclear War, 1962 (Box 22)
    - Session VII, Limited War, 1962 (Box 22)
    - Session VIII, Arms Control, 1962 (Box 22)
    - Session IX, Disarmamentr, 1962 (Box 22)
    - Session X, The Prospects Before Us, 1962 (Box 22)
  - Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies, 1965-1967; annual report drafts and related material (Box 23)
    See also Subject files: Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies
  - "Avenues to the Arts"
    See also Subject files: "Avenues to the Arts"
    - Incomplete set, 1959 (Box 23)
    - Drafts, compilations (Sessions I-VI) (Box 23)
    - Drafts of outlines, etc (Box 23)
    - Permissions, literature, 1959-1962 Jun (Box 23)
    - Permissions, literature, 1962 Jul - 1963 (Box 23)
    - Permissions, music, 1959 Feb - 1959 Apr (Box 23)
    - Permissions, music, 1959 May - 1962 Mar (Box 24)
    - Readings (1-2) (Box 24)
    - Readings (3-8) (Box 24)
    - Readings (10-11) (Box 24)
  - Business programs, miscellaneous, 1961-1963 (Box 24)
  - Capitol Hill Seminar proposal, 1961-1963; 2 folders (Box 24)
    See also Subject files: Capitol Hill Seminar
  - Carnegie Readings Project, 1963-1965 (Box 24)
  - "The Citizen and the New Age of Science", 1960-1963; proposal for a program and final report (Box 25)
    See also Publications: Publication brochure and proposal for "The Citizen and the New Age of Science"
  - Conference on Mass Media: Criticism of the Arts, 1966-1967 (Box 25)
  - Developing Responsible Public Leadership, 1961-1963 (Box 25)
  - Diplomat's Reading Program, 1965-1966 (Box 25)
  - Discussion Program on Urbanism, 1964; outline draft (Box 25)
  - The Executive Seminar
    - [General], 1959-1961; 2 folders (Box 25)
    - Permissions, 1958-1959 (Box 25)
  - "Explorations of the Universe"
    - Discussion guide for text edition of draft, circa 1962 (Box 25)
    - Discussion leader's guide (Box 26)
    - Memphis Adult Education Center, 1962 (Box 26)
    - NET television series, 1961-1962 (Box 26)
    - New York reception, 1962-1963 (Box 26)
    - Outline, undated (Box 26)
    - Suggestions for use of study-discussion program, 1963 (Box 26)
    - Washington reception, 1963 (Box 26)
  - Japan seminar, 1966-1967 (Box 26)
  - KZSU Radio, Stanford University, 1963-1966 (Box 26)
  - Labor education, 1960-1962 (Box 26)
  - "Man and the Modern Community", undated; proposals (Box 26)
  - Mass Media Program, 1958-1961 (Box 26)
  - "Mystery of Matter"
    - Experimental groups, 1963 (Box 26)
    - Fort Worth Public Library, 1963 (Box 26)
    - Proposal outline, undated (Box 26)
    - University of Wyoming, 1963 (Box 26)
    - Western Reserve University, 1963 (Box 26)
  - Oak Ridge (ORINS) Project, 1963-1965; general correspondence (Box 26)
  - Oak Ridge Summer Institute, 1963-1965; various papers (Box 26)
  - Parent Education Project, 1959 (Box 27)
  - Peace Corps
    See also Subject files: Peace Corps Project
    - General, 1960-1962 (Box 27)
    - Negotiated contract, 1966 (Box 27)
  - Peace Corps Project
    - Asilomar costs, 1967 (Box 27)
    - Commentaries, 1966 (Box 27)
    - Conference for Project Directors, 1967 (Box 27)
    - Confidential assessment reports, 1962-1966 (Box 27)
    - Contracts and financial papers, 1967 (Box 27)
    - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 27)
    - Director's training program, 1962 (Box 27)
    - Permissions to publish, 1966 (Box 27)
    - Proposal, 1965 (Box 27)
    - Returned Volunteers' Conference, evaluations 1-7, 1967 (Box 27)
    - Returned Volunteers' Meetings, 1965-1966 (Box 28)
    - Returned Volunteers' Program, final report, 1967 (Box 28)
    - Various papers, 1967 (Box 28)
  - Peace Corps Seminar
    - Discussion leader's guide, Vol. 1 (Vol. 2 missing), 1966 (Box 28)
    - Discussion leader's guide, Vols. 3-5, 1966 (Box 28)
    - Discussion leader's guide, Vols. 6-8, 1966 (Box 28)
  - "Peace in the Western World" Project, 1967 (Box 27)
  - "Powerful Newspapers" Conference, 1966-1967 (Box 27)
  - Proposals
    - Drafts, undated (Box 29)
    - National Science Foundation, [ca. 1960-1961] (Box 29)
    - "Pilot Redevelopment Education Program", undated (Box 29)
    - Proposals by AFCE, 1962-1963 (Box 29)
    - Various areas, 1965-1966 (Box 29)
    - "The World of the Atlantic", undated (Box 29)
  - Public Careers for Retired Corporate Executives, 1964-1966 (Box 29)
  - RPCV meeting, 1967; group distributions materials (Box 29)
  - Science and Religion Project, 1964 (Box 29)
  - Science Program
    See also Subject files: Science Program
    - Clippings and articles, 1959-1963 (Box 29)
    - Draft of parts 4-9, undated (Box 29)
    - Memoranda and printed material, 1957-1960 (Box 29)
    - Printed material, 1958-1969 (Box 30)
    - Promotion, undated (Box 30)
    - Various papers, 1960-1964 (Box 30)
  - "Theological Renewal", 1966 (Box 30)
  - Third Southwest Seminar in Public Responsibility, 1961-1962 (Box 30)
  - United Steelworkers of America
    - Proposal for Institute on Men and Labor, 1962 (Box 30)
    - "Men and American Society", 1961 (Box 30)
    - Staff training conference, 1960 (Box 30)
  - Young Presidents' Organization, 1966-1967 (Box 30)
- Publications
  - Advanced Management Training Program, 1960; evaluation report on (Box 30)
  - Carson, Pirie, Scott, Publishers, 1961 (Box 30)
  - Case histories, 1962 (Box 30)
  - Complimentary and review copies, lists of, 1962-1963 (Box 30)
  - Copyrights, 1961 (Box 30)
  - Critical Issues and Decisions: A Program for Federal Executives, 1962-1963; reprint permissions (Box 30)
  - Discussion Leaders' Manual, revised edition, 1962 (Box 30)
  - Discussion Manual, draft, undated (Box 31)
  - "Education and Democracy", undated (Box 31)
  - "Freedom of the Press," chapter VII, undated (Box 31)
  - "Man in the Political Community", 1965-1967 (Box 31)
  - "Manual for Leaders of Adult Discussion Groups on World Politics" (AFPE), 1951-1954 (Box 31)
  - McGraw-Hill Publishers, 1962 (Box 31)
  - Miscellaneous forms and agreements, 1965-1966 (Box 31)
  - Permissions
    - General, 1963-1965 (Box 31)
    - "Law and the Lawless", 1968 (Box 31)
      See also Subject files: "Law and the Lawless"
    - McGraw-Hill, 1962-1965 (Box 31)
  - "Population in Perspective" (Louise Young, editor), 1967-1968; outline (Box 31)
  - Production schedules, 1962 (Box 31)
  - Proofs and original copy for outstanding manuscripts, undated (Box 31)
  - "Programs and Publicatons" brochure, undated (Box 31)
  - Publication brochure and proposal for "The Citizen and the New Age of Science", 1963 (Box 31)
    See also Programs and projects: "The Citizen and the New Age of Science"
  - Publications in continuing education, 1967-1968 (Box 31)
  - Publications list for former CSLEA, 1952-1963 (Box 31)
  - Publications pamphlet, photo-ready copy, various dates (Box 32)
  - Publishers, various papers, 1961-1962 (Box 32)
  - Radio scripts, Harold Williams, 1966 (Box 32)
  - Transfer papers for copyrights, 1962 (Box 32)
  - Westinghouse permissions, 1963 (Box 32)
  - "What is the Nature of Science?", undated; 3 folders (Box 32)
- Subject files
  - Adult Education Association (AEA), 1959-1964 (Box 33)
  - African Leadership Project, 1962 (Box 12)
    See also Programs and projects: African Leadership Project
  - American Assembly, 1961-1963 (Box 33)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1961-1963 (Box 33)
  - American Association of University Women, 1951-1967; study guides and various papers (Box 33)
  - American Foundation for Political Education (AFPE)
    See also Administrative files: Statistical information (AFPE)
    - "A Statement Concerning [its] Character, Activities, Purposes, Future Plans and Financial Condition", 1948 (Box 33)
    - Evaluation report (J.E. Ivey) and related papers, 1952-1953 (Box 33)
    - Study of American Foundation for Political Education, 1954 (Box 33)
  - American Management Association, 1959-1961 (Box 33)
  - Annual reports, State of Illinois, 1953-1958 (Box 12)
  - Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies
    See also Programs and projects: Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies
    - Communications Conference, 1965-1966 (Box 34)
    - Selections from the 1963 lecture series (Box 34)
    - Selections from the 1965 Lecture Series (Box 34)
  - Aspen Society of Fellows, 1964-1966 (Box 34)
  - Atlantic Council of the U.S., 1963-1964 (Box 34)
  - "Avenues to the Arts", 1957-1963; 2 folders (Box 13)
    See also Programs and projects: "Avenue to the Arts"
  - Capitol Hill seminar, 1962-1963 (Box 13)
    See also Programs and projects: Capitol Hill Seminar proposal
  - Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions, 1962-1963 (Box 34)
  - Chicago Council on Foreign Relations, 1960-1962; seminar and various papers (Box 34)
  - Chicago World Politics Program, 1956-1962 (Box 34)
  - Committee for the Study of Mankind, 1958-1961 (Box 34)
  - Committee of Correspondence, 1960-1962 (Box 34)
  - Congressional investigations, 1952-1953 (Box 35)
  - Council of National Organizations, 1960-1961; 1962 (Box 35)
  - "Discovering Modern Poetry", 1960-1961 (Box 13)
  - "Education for Public Responsibility", 1961 (Box 13)
  - Educational television, printed material, 1960 (Box 35)
  - Encampment for Citizenship, 1960 (Box 35)
  - Film conference with UCLA, 1965-1966 (Box 35)
  - Foreign Policy Association, Committee on Community Development, 1960-1964 (Box 35)
  - Fund Raising Institute, 1966 (Box 35)
  - Grants from foundations, 1961-1965 (Box 13)
  - Great Books Foundation, 1960-1962 (Box 35)
  - Harvard Business School Association, 1960 (Box 35)
  - Illinois Statewide Conference on Adult Education, 1962 (Box 35)
  - Institute for International Order, 1960-1961 (Box 36)
  - Kawin, Ethel, 1962 (Box 36)
  - "Law and the Lawless", 1967-1969 (Box 13)
    See also Publications: Permissions: "Law and the Lawless"
  - Law-Science Academy of America, 1966-1967 (Box 36)
  - Legislation, undated (Box 36)
  - Living Library, 1962-1963 (Box 36)
  - National Center of Communication Arts and Sciences, 1966 (Box 36)
  - National Council of the Churches of Christ, 1963-1964 (Box 36)
  - National Educational Television, 1959-1963 (Box 36)
  - National Science Foundation, 1953-1969 (Box 36)
  - National University Extension Association
    - General material, 1961 (Box 36)
    - Progress report of the Community Development Division, 1961-1962 (Box 36)
    - NUEA Conference, 1962 (Box 36)
  - Pasadena (area) Liberal Arts Center, 1961-1962 (Box 36)
  - Peace Corps. project, 1966 (Box 13)
    See also Projects and Programs: Peace Corps; Projects and Programs: Peace Corps Project; Projects and Programs: Peace Corps Seminar
  - Press analyses, magazine articles, 1948-1959 (Box 36)
  - Promotion letters, 1962-1963 (Box 36)
  - Publishers (science publications), 1961-1962 (Box 14)
  - Science program, 1957-1969; 3 folders (Box 14)
    See also Projects and Programs: Science Program
  - Scientists' Committee for Radiation Information, 1963 (Box 36)
  - Society for International Development, 1962-1963 (Box 36)
  - Strategy for Peace Conference, 1962-1963 (Box 37)
  - Thomas More Institute, 1961-1962 (Box 37)
  - University of British Columbia, 1961-1962 (Box 37)
  - University of Illinois, World Affairs Programs, 1965 (Box 37)
  - University of Miami, Faculty Training Institute, 1961-1964 (Box 37)
  - University of Wisconsin, Alumni Seminar, 1962 (Box 37)
  - Urban renewal, 1965-1967; clippings (Box 37)
  - Urban renewal, 1963; miscellaneous (Box 14)
  - Westinghouse Electric Corp. Seminars, 1961-1963 (Box 37)
  - Wingspread Assembly on National Goals, 1959-1961 (Box 37)
- Miscellaneous
  - Newsletters, 1954-1961 (Box 37)
  - Printed material, 1954-1961 (Box 37)
  - Printed material, 1962-1966 (Box 38)
  - Publications (non-AFCE), 1959-1965 (Box 38)
  - Science newsletter layouts, undated (Box 38)
  - "Visiting Scholars in the United States", 1966-1967 (Box 38)
  - "Worldwide Register of Adult Education, 1965 (Box 38)
  - Unidentified and fragments, various dates (Box 38)